next up we have
Brendan and Andreas can take it away.
And and Jenny
and. Yes.
Okay. So
I'll try and do a quick introduction here.
So what we're going to talk about today
is a project that's called New Beginnings.
Never do the actual thing.
And this was a collective writing project
where 48 authors used
a custom edit machine
to write a collaborative text.
And this took place
during the Toast Festival in 2023,
which is a literary festival in
Harvick Spec, which is near Minster,
Germany.
We I mean, all of us,
the three of us
who sort of conceived and made the
there were 48 writers,
but there were three of us who sort of
put the concept together
and made the thing work. And
we're here today, and
unfortunately,
we don't have time to do all the bios,
but also our bios are going to try
and keep brief.
But so just a few words though.
Yanny Boone is the program director
and deputy
artistic director
at Book Who's Center for literature.
She's based in Cologne, Germany,
but the institution
book is in Harvick
spec, which is, as I said, near Minster.
Andreas is also doing a lot of different
things.
He's independent artist and researcher.
One of he's a
he has a sort of label, so to speak,
where they publish sonic poetry
and language based sound works.
And he currently lives in Hamburg,
Germany, and I'm Brendan, I live in
Berlin, Germany, and I'm an independent
artist and a reluctant engineer.
So this
concept was it was a collaboration
between the three of us.
It borrows from some ideas
from some earlier experiments
that I started,
you know, more than 15 years ago now.
It was a series.
It was called Exquisite Code.
And this project here was a kind of reboot
and a and a rewrite
with some different mechanics.
And it was in a very different context
from what I'd done before,
especially because we're all the writers
were mostly writing in German.
And there also the people involved
were also sort of discursive,
more active in more German
speaking artistic scenes.
And there's actually
also quite a diversity among the writers
in terms of their practices
and their backgrounds. And
we don't have a lot of time.
And it's slightly complicated.
The thing worked.
Not too convoluted,
but hopefully we can give you an idea
of the sort of novel,
interesting and fun parts of the project.
Okay, so I'll hand it over to Yeni
to give you some background.
Hello everybody,
and thank you for the introduction.
My part is in the introduction as well
to the project New Beginnings,
which was in 48 hours.
Human machine collective writing, books
print conceived like said Andreas
Brand and me.
But it was based on
Brendan's program The Maggot.
And over 48 hours, 48
authors each wrote for one hour
into a dedicated writing interface.
So there were people were poets, prose
writers, artists and scholars.
The project was like printed, embedded
in a festival,
which seemed the theme of the festival
was I mean, the
which is an old German word for comments.
And that question was became the question
for new beginnings itself.
So who owns the text?
What does Arthur ship mean
when a text is written by 48 people,
none of whom control the whole?
What happens to autonomy and to copyright
once your individual writing
is pulled by the machine without credit
and folded into a collective text
far bigger than any single contribution
for the whole project you see now.
Also the cover
and the back cover of the publication,
because the project became a publication,
which you can see now.
And for this
we work with the process design
studio OSP,
who developed a dynamic font.
So each author was assigned
with the customized font.
You can see this on the cover
in the different type fonts that spell out
new beginnings.
And throughout the book itself,
the shifting type shows that different
voices are writing without revealing
which customized font belongs
to which author.
That's quite
important that there was so no copyright
or to one author possible. So.
And during the 48 hours of text
as it developed, was shown at the festival
and as well on the website, once
all writing slots were complete,
there was a small reading on the festival
site, but shortly after all
text was published on the website SaPD
and as a print on demand book
available to order, which Andreas
will show later because he's the
only one who found it in his
between his books. So.
And now I will pass to Andreas,
who will tell you something
about interface and the mode of writing.
Yes. Thank you.
I will open the next slide.
Right.
So the text was staged as a
as a collective whole
without negating its anonymous polyphony.
And this model of collectivity
was achieved via machining or a rhythmic
editing process
that gave the 48 authors heavily
time boxed writing tasks,
and to design and algorithmically inscribe
an editing process before.
Before there was content,
we had to make the writing
that would be produced
as input by the authors
slash users algorithmically manageable.
So we had to assume chunks of text
that would be automatically combined
by the editing algorithm to design
a book with chapters
as some sort of fill in the blank form.
These assumptions of a book or text to be
was enacted upon the authors,
as Jenny already said, via a sparse yet
effective interface, which you can see
in the screenshot right here.
So each author
was sent a link and which they could open
in their browser, and that this HTML
writing interface
and this interface provided them
with nothing more than a text box,
a timer, and a writing task.
Each author author was assigned one hour
of writing, divided into six writing
tasks with different timer lengths,
which were the following.
And I hope you can search enough
so you can also read it here.
So the first task was write
a response to a text left for you
by a previous participant.
Time 14 minutes two three.
Writing one of three.
Time five minutes three.
Free writing 2 or 3 time
ten minutes for free
writing 3 or 3 time seven minutes five.
Write a task for the person who will write
after you time five minutes six.
Corpus care added on the 200 words
generated from all previous texts
using a Markov algorithm
within three time 15 minutes seven.
Create a chapter title time three minutes.
The input from each task was pulled,
so to speak, by the system
when the timer ran out,
making further editing impossible.
Each chunk was then sorted and arranged
by the editing algorithm in a certain way,
which,
when we give some insights on after me.
But I want to finish
with three observations
on this domesticated writing process one.
Writing is always constrained
in the Olympian sense.
You gain back control
by making the rules that implicitly govern
your writing explicit, which we kind of
forced upon the authors of this method.
Two writing had to be domesticated
in order to be manageable
by the editing algorithm.
That is maybe something to keep in mind
that writing is turned into data
also by social media platforms
or the like.
And three the whole process
of making this, this performance
or publishing performance was imagining,
imagining,
making a book as a self-made social media
publishing form, a platform.
The text box that opens up services
like Twitter, Mastodon, Facebook
and the like, which requests you
to make an input in order to participate,
and the timeline algorithms that sort
collectively written text into an
endless stream resemble what we did
with requesting input by the authors
and creating this collaged stream
of input data.
Only this time
we got to decide the rules of the game.
So new beginnings might imagine literature
as an alternative reality
to the reality of social media
or digital media in general.
If you want to make a boat claim.
Yeah. Brenton.
Sorry.
Unmute myself first.
Yeah.
So if we can have a look at the flowchart.
This is my readable here.
It's a bit dry in a way,
but this is a very faithful
reproduction of the software's actual
mechanics and the way it worked.
So it was a fairly straightforward
sort of web application
written in Python
using a kind of minimal framework
called bottle and.
This helped to by constraining here
the complexity of the system
helped to make it reasonably reliable
for this particular thing.
And you can see
some of the typical,
I don't know, user interface problems.
You know, things like if someone is late
or if they're early or things like that,
how how we sort of cope with that
and make it hopefully still work for the
the author, that they can still write
something and contribute.
And Andreas,
can you scroll down a little bit
and then you can see here
where it gets a little bit more dynamic
than is where we're dealing with
either the, the sort of prompted input or
with the Markov stuff.
And again,
this was some ways very helpful to just
I was using plain text files
and a sort of home
brewed database system
rather than some sort of
more complex or exotic setup,
which made it a lot easier to then
just basically deal
with raw pieces of text on the
in various different folders and files.
So yeah, someone's interested.
We can, I think
have we published the code?
I think so I don't know
if there's a link to it, but yeah we did.
That's right.
That's it's I remember
if anyone's really interested,
you can certainly get in touch
to ask about the system or if you want to
repurpose it or use it, then feel free.
But I think we're almost out of time,
so I will stop there. To.
Andreas, do we have a conclusion?
This.
This was the conclusion I feel.
Okay, yeah,
that's.
True,
but I'm not sticking the landing here.
But anyway.
Yeah,
thanks.
Thank you.
All right.
Coming in early, we will have,
I think, plenty of time for questions.
We are also bumping up
against the lunch breaks.
We can go a bit longer,
but first we have Michael.
Go ahead and start whenever you're ready.
Okey dokey.
I'm going to share my screen here. And.